<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles ecclesiasticall to be inquired of by the churchwardens and the sworne-men within the dioces of Hereford in the first visitation of the reuerend father in God, Harbart Bishop of the said dioces: this present yeare M. D.LXXXVI. and in the XXVIII. yeare of the raigne of our most gracious soueraigne Lady Queene Elizabeth, &amp;c. And so hereafter, till the next visitation, &amp; from titme to time to be presented.</title>
            <title>Visitation articles. 1586</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Hereford. Bishop (1586-1602 : Westfaling)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00186</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120530</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855726</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855726</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21228</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00186)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21228)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 422:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles ecclesiasticall to be inquired of by the churchwardens and the sworne-men within the dioces of Hereford in the first visitation of the reuerend father in God, Harbart Bishop of the said dioces: this present yeare M. D.LXXXVI. and in the XXVIII. yeare of the raigne of our most gracious soueraigne Lady Queene Elizabeth, &amp;c. And so hereafter, till the next visitation, &amp; from titme to time to be presented.</title>
                  <title>Visitation articles. 1586</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Hereford. Bishop (1586-1602 : Westfaling)</author>
                  <author>Westfaling, Herbert, 1532?-1602.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes printer to the vniuersitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1586]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21228:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21228:1"/>
            <p>ARTICLES ECCLESIASTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CALL TO BE INQVIRED OF BY THE CHVRCHWARDENS AND THE SWORNE-MEN WITHIN THE dioces of Hereford in the firſt viſitation of the reuerend father in God, Harbart Biſhop of the ſaid dioces: this preſent yeare M.D.LXXXVI. and in the XXVIII. yeare of the raigne of our moſt gracious ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lady Queene Elizabeth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And ſo hereafter, till the next viſitation, &amp; from time to time to be preſented.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at Oxford by Ioſeph Barnes Printer to the vniuerſitie.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:21228:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21228:2"/>
            <head>ARTICLES TO BE INQVIRED of, in the Dioces of Hereford.</head>
            <p>FIRST ye ſhall enquire &amp; truly preſent vpon your oathes take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether you do know of any, which hath thruſt himſelf into any functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eccleſiaſtical without ordinary calling, as, to ſay publike ſeruice in Church or chappell, not being lawfully ordered Deacon at the leaſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether your Parſon or Vicar be known, ſuſpected or reported to haue bought his benefice, or come to it by any ſimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acall compact, made either by himſelf, or others, directly, or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly: or do let out his liuing or any part thereof to any, in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration that he hath obtained the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, curat, or miniſter, or anie other Prieſt or layman or woman doe wilfully maintain or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend any hereſies, falſe opinions or popiſh errors, contrary to the lawes of almightie God, and true doctrine, by publike authoritie now ſet foorth in this realme, and what be their names?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or curate, do not ſay co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prayer in your church, or chappel, diſtinctly &amp; reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, &amp; in ſuch order, as it is ſet foorth by publike authority, without any kind of alteration, &amp; at due &amp; conuenient hours: &amp; whether your miniſter do not ſo turne himſelfe, &amp; ſtand in ſuch place of your church or chancell, as the people may beſt heare the ſame, and whether the ſacraments be not likewiſe miniſtred reuerently in ſuch maner as by the lawes of this realm is appointed: &amp; whether vpon wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſdayes and fridayes the Letany and other praiers appointed for the day be not ſaid accordingly?</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whether your Miniſter or any other not being licenced take vpon him to expound ſcripture, &amp; therby omit vpon any ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the reading of a part of an Homily at the leaſt, or vpon any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion do omit the ſame?</p>
            <p n="6">6 Whether your Miniſter do not read the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mination againſt
<pb facs="tcp:21228:3"/>ſinners, with certaine praiers appointed, at the leaſt thrice a yeere beſides the lent time: and whether he doth not read the Queenes Maieſties iniunctions quarterly in the Church?</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> Whether he haue preached or cauſed to be preached his monethly or quarterly Sermons at the leaſt, and who they be that preached them, and whether he haue ſuffered any not licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to preach, or forbidden any that was licenced?</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> Whether any notorious offender, or which is out of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or excommunicate, or a ſtranger of an other pariſh, be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the communion by your miniſter, or ſuch as being aboue twentie yeres of age haue not beene able to ſay at the leaſt the Lords prayer, ten commandements, and Articles of the beliefe, or being aboue fourteen yeres, &amp; vnder twenty, that could not ſay the Catechiſme: &amp; whether your miniſter at times conuenient be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he adminiſter vnto them, and namely before Eaſter, do vſe to examin his Pariſhioners, whether they can ſay by heart the ſame which is required in this behalfe: &amp; whether he marry any perſons, that were ſingle before, that cannot ſay the Catechiſme?</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9</hi> Whether your Miniſters on euery Sunday and Holyday in the after-noone before euening prayer do not inſtruct all the youth within your pariſh of conuenient age of both ſexes, in the Catechiſme, or at the leaſt ſo many of them by courſe as time wil ſerue, &amp; as he may wel hear &amp; inſtruce for half an hour ſpace at the leaſt, &amp; preſent to the Ordinary ſuch quarterly as refuſe to come to be catechiſed?</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10</hi> Whether he do diligently viſite the ſick &amp; comfort them with exhortation to contribute by wil for the reliefe of the Poore, as their abilitie ſhall ſerue?</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11</hi> Whether he be diligent in ſtudy of the holy Scriptures for further increaſe in knowledge, and for that purpoſe hath (if hee bee vnder the degree of a Maiſter of Arte) at the leaſt,
<pb facs="tcp:21228:3"/>the new Teſtament in Latine, &amp; Engliſh, and whether he doth daily conferre certaine Chapters thereof together, vſing at va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant times ſuch good and ſeemly exerciſes as may keepe him from ſluggiſhnes and idlenes?</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12</hi> Whether any myniſter haue maried any in times for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by the Eccleſiaſticall Lawes, or without bannes thrice asked, otherwiſe than by licence of the ordinary, or hath vſed the forme of thanks giuing, for a woman after childebirth, being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully begotten with childe otherwiſe than in forme of a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninent perſon, <hi>viz.</hi> in a white ſheet or other habit preſcribed by the ordinary, or vpon any other day than on a Sunday, or Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day: or before ſufficient caution taken, that ſhee ſhould not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the Pariſhe, till ſhee ſhould performe ſuch pennance, as ſhould be enioyned by the Ordinary?</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13</hi> Whether your Miniſter vſe any other Rite, or Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in the Church than is preſcribed by the booke of Common Praier, and whether he or any other, keep or vſe any ſecret Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles, Preachings, Lectures, or Readings contrary to the Lawe, and what be their names?</p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14</hi> Whether your Parſon, or Vicar: doth not in his owne perſon at the Church, ſometimes in the Yeare, both ſay Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Prayers himſelfe, and alſo adminiſter the holy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to the booke of Common Praier?</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15</hi> Whether your Miniſter vſe the dayes of Perambulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons accuſtomed, and that without wearing of any Surples, or any other Rite, or ſtaying at any olde Croſſe, and alſo without vſing any other Praiers, than the <hi>103.</hi> and <hi>104. Pſalmes,</hi> an Homily for that purpoſe, the Letanie, and ſuch ſentences of the Scripture as are appointed by Iniunction in that behalfe?</p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16</hi> Whether any do ſerue as a Miniſter, or Deacon not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenced vnder the Ordinaries Seale, or ſerue twoo cures, and
<pb facs="tcp:21228:4"/>whether any Miniſter comming out of an other Dioces hath not the Ordinaries letters teſtimoniall concerning aſwell the cauſe of his departure as his behauiour, and what ſtipend your Curate hath by yeere?</p>
            <p n="17">
               <hi>17</hi> Whether is your miniſter a peacemaker and exhorter of his Pariſhioners to Chriſtian loue, &amp; concord, and ſuch a one as is no ſower of diſcorde amongſt Neighbours?</p>
            <p n="18">
               <hi>18</hi> Whether your Parſon or Vicar ſuffer his buildings or Chauncel to fall to ruine or decay, and whether he or anie other haue taken away or diſcouered any Church, Chappell, or Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, or any part of them: any Church porch, veſtrie, ſpittle, almes houſe, or ſuch like: or hath pulled downe the belles, or hath made any ſpoile or waſte vppon his benefice, either in his timber, or woods, or by felling trees in the Church-yarde?</p>
            <p n="19">
               <hi>19</hi> Whether the Miniſter and Church-wardens (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to hir Maieſties Iniunctions) doe keepe well the Regiſter book, &amp; therin regiſter al Weddings, buriengs, &amp; Chriſtenings, and once euery yeere exhibite a Copie thereof by Indenture to the office of thordinaries Regiſter: and if it be not done, through whoſe default?</p>
            <p n="20">
               <hi>20</hi> Whether your Miniſter hath put in vre ſuch orders concerning Catechiſing of youth, &amp;c. and executed all other ſuch things as hath from time to time ſince the laſt viſitation, beene ſent vnto him from the Ordinary, as proceſſes, &amp; ſuch like: And whether he hath made any Certificats of penance orderly &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitently done, which hath indeed bin ſcoffingly, or impenitently performed, or els not done at all?</p>
            <p n="21">
               <hi>21</hi> Whether your Parſon, or Vicar hath at anie time ſince the thirteenth yeere of the Queenes Maieſties raigne, made anie manner of leaſe, or graunt, of his Parſonage, or Vicarage, or anie part thereof (hee being abſent, and not reſident
<pb facs="tcp:21228:4"/>vpon the ſame) to any other then to his Curate that did, or doth ſerue his Cure in his abſence?</p>
            <p n="22">
               <hi>22</hi> Whether is your Parſon, or Vicar abſent from among you aboue eightie daies in anie one yeere in all, not being lawfully qualified and diſpenced withall, and beeing ſo licenced, whether is the Cure ſerued by an honeſt learned Curate, whether doth hee not at the leaſt for one month in the yere, keepe hoſpitalitie at his liuing, and alſo giue, if his benefice be aboue twentie poundes a yeere, the fortith part thereof to the Poore?</p>
            <p n="23">
               <hi>23</hi> Whether any Miniſter do forſake his function &amp; giue himſelfe to any other trade of life then is fit, or may be incident with that calling?</p>
            <p n="24">
               <hi>24</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter keepe any ſuſpected woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his houſe, or (being not married) any woman not of neere kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto him, or doth he liue in any tauerne, or alehowſe, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly reſort thither, or is he a hawker, or hunter, or a gameſter, at any game, other then at ſhooting, or otherwiſe ſuſpected of any notorious crime, or any euill example of life?</p>
            <p n="25">
               <hi>25</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter keepe, or ſuffer to be kept any Alehouſe, Tauern, or Victualing houſe in his Parſonage or Vicarage houſe?</p>
            <p n="26">
               <hi>26</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter vſe any exceſſiue or vnſeemely kinde of apparell not commendable in that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling?</p>
            <p n="27">
               <hi>27</hi> Whether doth the Patrone ſuffer the Church to lie voide without incumbent, and take any the profites thereof, and how long he hath ſo done?</p>
            <p n="28">
               <hi>28</hi> Whether the Patron haue freely beſtowed the benefice without any Simony, directly, or indirectly, betweene him &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:21228:5"/>the incumbent, or any other: And whether he doth not retaine his owne tithes, or hath the benefice whereof he is Patrone, or ſome part thereof in farme?</p>
            <p n="29">
               <hi>29</hi> Whether your Schoolemaſter teaching within your Pariſh openly, or within any Gentle-mans houſe be licenced thereunto by the ordinary: whether doth he teach ſuch books as be commanded to be taught, and that diligently? And whether is he reputed of ſincere Religion, and conuerſation, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenteth Diuine ſeruice, or no?</p>
            <p n="30">
               <hi>30</hi> Whether haue you in your Pariſh Church, or Chappel the booke of Common Praier, with the new Rallender, two Pſalters, the great Engliſh Bible, the two Volumes of Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, the Paraphraſe of Eraſmus in Engliſh, the Table of the Ten commandements, whole, and vntorne, a conuenient Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, a decent Communion Table on a frame, a Linnen Cloth to couer the ſame, with ſome other couering of Silke or ſuch like, a Communion Cup, and a couer of Siluer, a decent Surpleſe with ſleeues, a ſure Coffer with two lockes for the Regiſter booke, a ſtrong Cheſt for the Almes Bore, with three lockes thereunto, and all other things requiſite?</p>
            <p n="31">
               <hi>31</hi> Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, Curate, or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter weare any Cope in your Pariſh Church or Chappell, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the holy Communion in any Chalice heretofore vſed at Maſſe, or in any prophane Cup or Glaſſe?</p>
            <p n="32">
               <hi>32</hi> Whether are all Altars taken downe, to the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and the place Whited, and paued vnder-neath, and the Roode-lofte downe to the Croſſe-beame, al ſuperſtitious books vſed either in the Church or otherwiſe defaced, togither with all monuments of Superſtition and Idolatry, as Veſtiments, &amp;c. And if not, in whoſe cuſtody are they, or any of them?</p>
            <p n="33">
               <hi>33</hi> Whether any Church-wardens ſince the laſte viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:21228:5"/>haue ſuffered any vnmaried woman begotten with childe to depart their Pariſh before ſuch pennance done as was inioyned?</p>
            <p n="34">
               <hi>34</hi> Whether is your Church, chappel, or chauncell ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently repaired, and churchyard decently and ſufficiently fenced, and kept cleane: if not, in whoſe default?</p>
            <p n="35">
               <hi>35</hi> Whether haue your churchwardens from time to time truly leuied xii. pence for euery day, of thoſe who abſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from church, and whether hath the ſame beene beſtowed vpon the poore as it ought, or no: And whether the churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens themſelues haue abſented themſelues, or beene negligent in their duty, or in frequenting diuine ſeruice, and whether doth your Miniſter admoniſh the churchwardens ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in the church after the ſecond leſſon at morning and euening praier to looke to their charge in this behalfe?</p>
            <p n="36">
               <hi>36</hi> Whether haue any churchwardens or ſwornmen, ſince the laſt viſitation or inquiſition, or at any time, concealed any diſorder or crime done in your Pariſh, or not preſented the ſame to be reformed?</p>
            <p n="37">
               <hi>37</hi> Whether any churchwardens without iuſt cauſe delai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to giue account euerie yeare of the church goods, or detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth any of the church goods, or common ſtocke, and whether is the ſtock of the poore mans boxe faithfully, and indifferently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed to the poore without any partiall affection?</p>
            <p n="38">
               <hi>38</hi> Whether any churchwardens haue continued in that office, at any time aboue one yeare without a newe election?</p>
            <p n="39">
               <hi>39</hi> Whether the clerke be appointed, according to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of your Pariſh, whether is he obedient to the miniſter in ſuch things, as belong to his office, &amp; vſeth diligence in keeping al ſuch things as belong to his charge, decent &amp; cleane: whether is he able to read diſtinctly, &amp; to anſwere as appertaineth to him
<pb facs="tcp:21228:6"/>in the church, &amp; whether is hee ſuffered to read any thing in the church, ſaue the one leſſon and the epiſtle?</p>
            <p n="40">
               <hi>40</hi> Whether when any man is paſſing out of this life, the Bel be not touled, to moue the people to pray for the ſick perſon, and whether there be any ringing for any that died out of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, &amp; whether in the pariſh there be any more ringing than one ſhort peale before, &amp; an other after the buriall: &amp; whether on All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoules euen or day, or any Saints euen, or vpon any abrogate ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidaies, there be any other ringing than is vſual, on co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king dates, or other than ringing to common praier, or ſermons, &amp; that but moderate: &amp; whether there be any ringing at al in time of common praier, reading of homilies, or of preaching?</p>
            <p n="41">
               <hi>41</hi> Whether any Lords of miſrule, dauncers, plaiers, or any other diſguiſed perſons do dance, or play any vnſeemly parts in the Church, Church-yard, or Chappel-yard, or whether are there any playes or common drinking kept in church, or Church-yarde, who maintaine &amp; accompany ſuch?</p>
            <p n="42">
               <hi>42</hi> Whether any perſon in your pariſh hath remained ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated by the ſpace of fortie daies, &amp; whether any ſuch doe intrude himſelfe to diuine ſeruice, the Sacrament, or publike aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, and who are encoragers and keepers of company with ſuch as ſo remaine excommunicate?</p>
            <p n="43">
               <hi>43</hi> Whether any holy daies, or Fiſhdaies abrogated by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, are either by your miniſter bidden, or by any other obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſuperſtitiouſly, or any feſtiual daies vſed a new by any with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out lawfull authority?</p>
            <p n="44">
               <hi>44</hi> Whether all ſuperiours, as parents, maſters, &amp;c. do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as in them lieth to bring to the church to be catechiſed on holy daies &amp; Sundaies in the afternoone before euening praier, their children, ſeruants, and apprentices both mankind and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mankind being aboue ſeuen yeares of age, and vnder twenty, or
<pb facs="tcp:21228:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>at the leaſt ſuch &amp; ſo many, as your miniſter ſhall thinke meete to be ſent thither for that purpoſe: and there diligently &amp; obediently to heare and to be ordered by the miniſter vntil ſuch time as they haue learned the ſame Catechiſme: &amp; what their names be that neglect ſo to doe: and who betwixt the ſaide ages cannot ſay the Catechiſme?</p>
            <p n="45">
               <hi>45</hi> Whether there be any that refuſe to come to diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in their pariſh Church, or Chappell, or doe not frequent the ſame, or doe not being of conuenient age communicate thrice a yere at the leaſt, &amp; namely once about Eaſter, or receiuing have not ſignified the ſame to the miniſter in tyme conuenient, that he might examine them how they were inſtructed for partaking of ſo high myſteries: and whether there bee any ſtrangers, that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourne in your pariſh, eſpecially about Eaſter, and do abſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from Church: or any that be hinderers or deriders of true religion, or of thoſe which profeſſe it?</p>
            <p n="46">
               <hi>46</hi> Whether there be any lay or temporall man, not being within orders, or any child, that hath or enioyeth any benefice or ſpirituall promotion?</p>
            <p n="47">
               <hi>47</hi> Whether any in your Pariſh be ſuſpected to reſort to any Maſſe, or other kind of ſeruice than is receiued by authority, or to be reconciled to the Church of Rome, or do goe vp &amp; downe in ſecretwiſe or diſguiſed, or that haue beene not long ſithence beyond the Seas, being no merchants, vſing traficke, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe lawfully licenced?</p>
            <p n="48">
               <hi>48</hi> Whether any do pray in an vnknowen tongue, or vpon beads, or do any way number their praiers ſuperſtitiouſly, or do read, ſel, or deliuer, any popiſh books come from beyond the ſeas.</p>
            <p n="49">
               <hi>49</hi> Whether any be in your pariſh which at time of diuine prayers do vſe any iangling, talking, walking, or other vnſeeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behauior in church or churchyard, or do any way diſturbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer, or any part of the diuine ſeruice, or do vſe any game,
<pb facs="tcp:21228:7"/>or paſtime abroad at thoſe times, or ſit in the tauern, or alehouſe, or ſtreetes at ſuch times, or which doe worke on Sundaies, any handicraft worke, or which keepe open any ſhoppes for ſale of wares til euening praier be finiſhed, or which depart before prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers bee finiſhed, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth late without cauſe ſufficient, or which be brawlers, or fighters in the church or churchyard:</p>
            <p n="50">50 Whether any in your pariſh be knowen, or ſuſpected to vſe any witchcraft, or ſorcerie, charme, inchantment, or vnlawful inuocation, and namely, Midwiues at the labor of women, or any who do take vpon them to tel deſtinies, or to guide men to things loſt, or any that reſorteth vnto ſuch for helpe &amp; counſaile, or final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any blaſphemers of the name of God, or ſwearers among you:</p>
            <p n="51">51 Whether any be known, or ſuſpected to be adulterers, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicators, inceſtuous perſons, bawdes, or recettors of incontinent perſons into their houſes, or which conuey or ſuffer them to goe away before they do make ſatisfaction to the congregation offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, any drunkards, ribalds, malicious, contentious, and vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable perſons, common ſlaunderers, raylers, ſcoulders, or ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of diſcord amongſt you:</p>
            <p n="52">52 Whether any childe being born ſince the <hi>13.</hi> yeare of the Queenes Maieſties raigne hath not been brought to be baptiſed to your pariſh church, but hath beene baptiſed at home, or their baptiſme differred:</p>
            <p n="53">53 Whether your hoſpitales, ſpittles, &amp; almes-houſes be well &amp; godly vſed, according to the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>datio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ancient ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the ſame. Whether there be any other placed in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then poore, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, &amp; needy perſons, that haue not whereby, or wherwith to liue.</p>
            <p n="54">54 Whether there be any man that hath, or hath had at one time two wiues, or a woman two husbandes, any maried within degrees of conſanguinity, or affinity, ſet foorth in a table for that purpoſe, any diuorced keeping company ſtil togither, any maried without the degrees forbidden, which without law haue forſaken
<pb facs="tcp:21228:7"/>their wiues or huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, or liue not togither, any maried that haue made preco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tracts to other, any that haue made priuy contracts, or maried without conſent of their parents, or gouernors, any maried without bannes thriſe ſolemnly asked, or out of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh church where the ſolemnization ought to haue been, without the Ordinaries licence vnder his ſeale:</p>
            <p n="55">55 Whether there be any that directly, or indirectly, do take any vſury, or intereſt, who they be &amp; what is the maner of their vſury:</p>
            <p n="56">56 Whether any ſet downe in the laſt will and teſtament, of any, as executors, do preſume to execute, or deal with the deads goods before the wil be proued, or any preſume to adminiſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore adminiſtration committed vnto them, any hinderers of the performance of ſuch wil, any forgers, or changers of wils, or any executors which haue not fulfilled their teſtators will, eſpecially in not paying legacies giuen to good and godly vſes:</p>
            <p n="57">57 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens &amp; ſwornemen, &amp; euery of them certifie in writing vnder their handes &amp; ſeales to their Ordinary of the Dioces, or his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car general the names &amp; ſurnames of al thoſe perſons that abſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hearing the diuine ſeruice (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to hir Maieſties lawes) according to the iniunction giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that behalf, quarterly to be made, or at the leaſtwiſe in time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before ech the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or quarter ſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the ſaid dioces of Hereford:</p>
            <p n="58">58 Whether do you know, or haue you hard of any man or woman that hath practized, or doth practiſe Phiſicke or ſurgery within this dioces of Hereford, not being licenced ſo to doe by thordinary of the ſame, vnder his hand and ſeale, according to the Statute in that caſe prouided, &amp; what is his, or her name which doth, or hath ſo done:</p>
            <p n="59">59 Whether the Archdeacon, Chauncelor, Commiſſarie, Official, or any other vſing eccleſiaſtical iuriſdiction in this dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, their regiſtrars, or arctuaries, apparitors, or ſummoners,
<pb facs="tcp:21228:8"/>haue at any time wincked at &amp; ſuffered any adulteries, fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, inceſtes, or other faults &amp; offences, to paſſe &amp; remaine vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, &amp; vncorrected, for mony, rewards, bribes, pleaſure, friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or any other partiall or affectionate reſpect, or any of them haue bin burdenſome to any in this dioces, by exacting or taking exceſſiue fees, exceſſiue procurations, any rewards, or commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by the way of promotion, gift, contribution, help, redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of penance, omiſſion of quarter ſermons, obteining of any bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices or office, or any other like waies or meanes:</p>
            <p n="60">60 How many Adulteries, Inceſts, and Fornications, are notoriouſly knowen to haue bin committed in your Pariſh, ſince Eaſter. <hi>1585.</hi> how many offendors in any ſuch faults haue been put to open penance, &amp; openly corrected: and how many haue had their penance or any part thereof commuted, without conſent of the Biſhop himſelf firſt had, and what ſummes of mony laied by that means vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the offenders haue bin beſtowed vpon the poore of that Pariſh, or other godly vſes: and how many haue bin win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at, &amp; borne withal, or haue fined and paied mony to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, chanceler, commiſſary, Official, or their deputies, or to the Deanes, Regiſtrares, or Sumners, or any of them, for to eſcape open puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; what their names &amp; ſurnames be:</p>
            <p n="61">61 Whether the Deans Rurals, &amp; Sunners, or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do pay any annual rent, fee, or penſion for their offices, &amp; what they paie, and to whom:</p>
            <p n="62">62 Whether any haue been licenced to mary without the asking of bannes at al, or thrice asking, no ſufficient caution be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken before, that there was no impediment of precontract, conſanguinitie, affinitie, or any other lawful cauſe: &amp; that at time of granting the ſaid Licence there was no controuerſie, matter, or complaint mooued or depending before any eccleſiaſticall or ciuil iudge touching any ſuch lawful impediment of contracting matrimonie betweene ſuch perſons: and that the ſame parties ſhould not come to ſolemnize their marriage before they had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb facs="tcp:21228:8"/>the expreſſe aſſent &amp; conſent of their parents or gardians: &amp; further that the mariage of them ſhould be publikely ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the face of the church in meet &amp; conuenient time.</p>
            <p n="63">63 Whether in al excommunications for Hereſy, ſchiſme, Simony, periury, vſury, inceſt, adulterie, or any other grieuous crime, the ſentence haue been pronounced againſt any but in the proper perſon of a Biſhop, Deane, Archdeacon, or Prehendary, &amp; the ſame being within holy orders, &amp; hauing eccleſiaſtical iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction: and whether any Vicar general, official or commiſſarie not being within holy orders haue pronounced ſentence of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication againſt any for contumacie, but ſome learned mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, ſufficiently autoriſed therunto either by the Biſhop within his iuriſdiction, or by the Archdeacon within his, the Archdeacon being himſelfe alſo a miniſter.</p>
            <p n="64">64 Generally whether you knowe anie of the Queens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions, broken, or any other eccleſiaſticall matter worthy of redreſſe or no? &amp; if you do, by the oathes that you haue taken, you ſhal truly preſent it, aſwel now as hereafter, when it ſhal come to your knowledge:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <head>The tenor of the oath miniſtred to the Church-wardens &amp; ſwornmen.</head>
                        <p>YE ſhal ſwear by almighty God, that you ſhal diligently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider al &amp; euery the Articles giuen to you in charge, &amp; make a true anſwere vnto the ſame in writing, preſenting al and euery ſuch perſon, &amp; perſons dwelling within your pariſh, as haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any offence, or fault, or made any default mentioned in any of the ſame Articles, or which are vehemently ſuſpected, or defamed of any ſuch offence, fault, or default, wherein ye ſhal not preſent any perſon or perſons, of euill will, malice or hatred, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the truth, nor ſhal for loue, fauor, meed, dread, or any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt affection ſpare to preſent any that be offenders, ſuſpected, or defamed in any of theſe caſes, but ſhall do vprightly, as men ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the feare of god before your eies, and deſirous to maintaine vertue and ſuppreſſe vice, So God help you.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p n="65">
               <pb facs="tcp:21228:9"/>
65 Whether your Parſonage be impropriated, if it be, is it endued with a Vicarage, or is the Parſon bound onely to giue a penſion to a curate, and what is the penſion: to whom doth the proprietie of the Parſonage belong, who is the farmer thereof, and what is it worth yearely by common eſtimation:</p>
            <p n="66">66 Whether your Parſonage or Vicarage houſe, the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell or bodie of your church or chappell be in any decay and not ſufficiently repaired, and by whoſe default:</p>
            <p n="67">67 Whether your church ſtocke or any part thereof be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriftily waſted and ſpent: or other your church goodes, as gleebe land, rents or annuities, giuen to the better maintenance of your Church, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion cup, and ſuch like appertaining to the neceſſary vſe thereof, be giuen, ſolde, or any way alienated &amp; em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſled or turned to other vſe than by the lawes of the realme, it ought to be: by any of your Parſons, Vicars, Curates Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens, Sidemen, or other that hath or at any time had the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or ouerſight thereof:</p>
            <p n="68">68 Who is reputed &amp; taken to be the Patrone of your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage or vicarage: what quantity of gleebland belongeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: how many acres arable, how many of medow, how many of paſture, what feeding for ſheep &amp; other cattle, and what common. Alſo what howſes, what tythes and what priuiledges belong thereunto: <hi>This article ſhal you in ſeueral from the reſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in parchment and ſubſcribe your names.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="69">69 Whether do you know or haue heard of any benefice here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore in the remembrance of man preſentable or preſented vnto that doth now beare the name of an impropriation donatiue or any ſuch mixt title whereby the fruites of ſuch liuinges eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall is by ſubtill deuiſe of ſome greedie bodies chalenged and taken without right, or intereſt, &amp; how long hath the ſame ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued.</p>
            <p n="70">70 Whether the farmar of any impropriation doe chalenge the gift or enioying of the Vicarage thereof, or the tythes or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities or any part or parcell thereof, and by what title.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21228:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
